A new adventure is born.
The Land Before Time is a family, animation,
adventure film directed by Don Bluth.
An orphaned brontosaurus named Littlefoot sets off in
search of the legendary Great Valley.
A land of lush vegetation where the dinosaurs can thrive and live in peace.
Along the way he meets four other young dinosaurs, each one a different species, and they
encounter several obstacles as they learn to work together in order to survive.
Littlefoot (voice), played by Gabriel Damon.
Cera (voice), played by Candace Hutson.
Petrie (voice), played by Will Ryan.
Ducky (voice), played by Judith Barsi.
Littlefoot's Mother (voice), played by Helen Shaver.
Narrator / Rooter (voice), played by Pat Hingle.
The Land Before Time is a 1988 animated adventure drama film directed and co-produced by Don
Bluth from a screenplay by Stu Krieger and a story by Judy Freudberg and Tony Geiss.
Its executive producers are Steven Spielberg, George
Lucas, Kathleen Kennedy, and Frank Marshall.
The film stars the voices of Judith Barsi, Burke Byrnes, Gabriel Damon, Bill
Erwin, Pat Hingle, Candace Hutson, Will Ryan, and Helen Shaver.
It is the first film in the Land Before Time franchise.
Produced by Amblin Entertainment and Sullivan Bluth Studios, it
features dinosaurs living in prehistoric times.
The plot features a young brown Apatosaurus named Littlefoot, who ends up alone after
his mother dies protecting him from a villainous Tyrannosaurus rex.
Littlefoot flees famine and upheaval to search for the Great Valley, an area
spared from devastation, where the adult dinosaurs have moved on to.
On his journey, he meets four young companions: Cera, an orange Triceratops, Ducky, a green
Saurolophus, Petrie, a brown Pteranodon, and Spike, a green Stegosaurus.
The film explores issues of prejudice between the different species and the hardships they endure in their journey as they
are guided by the spirit of Littlefoot's mother and forced to deal with the Tyrannosaurus rex that killed her.
The Land Before Time is the only Don Bluth film of the 1980s in which Dom DeLuise did not participate (instead, he starred in Disney's Oliver & Company released
that same day), and the only film in the Land Before Time series that is not a musical, as well as the only one to be released theatrically worldwide.
It was also the last film that Bluth directed that was scored by James Horner,
executive produced by Spielberg, and distributed by Universal Pictures.
The film was released by Universal on November 18, 1988, to generally positive
reviews from critics and was a box office success, grossing $84.4 million.
Its success, along with An American Tail and the 1988 live-action/animated film Who Framed
Roger Rabbit, led Spielberg to found his animation studio, Amblimation.
The first film spawned a franchise with thirteen direct-to-video sequels, a television series, video games and merchandise, none of which had Bluth,
Spielberg nor Lucas' involvement (though Amblin Entertainment was involved in the television series like it was for Fievel's American Tails).
It is currently Don Bluth's second highest-grossing
animated film, only behind Anastasia (1997).
The film explores themes of vulkan, loss of loved one,
tyrannosaurus rex, earthquake, primitive time.
The tone is lighthearted.